Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Albums (Album File) circa 1880-circa 1980 (bulk 1860-1920) PR 2
New-York Historical Society
- [Cabinet card album of unidentified family], [1880-1899]; 14057 (Volume 210)
  Cabinet cards of unidentified family, and one memorial card of Henry Ward Beecher; most photographs made by Brooklyn photographers Gardner & Co., others by Mrs. E.G. Lacey of Morristown, and others by Philadelphia photographers.
- Photographs [Album of portraits, horseshoe motif on cover from the estate of Ina Love Thursby], [1890 and later]; 14055 (Volume 211)
  Portraits of men and women, made by Brooklyn and New York photographers including Pearsall, Bogardus, Kurtz, Meuer and others; primarily cabinet cards, and a few cartes-de-visite. See also album #18, 19.
- [Lawrie Family album], [1880-1899]; 14053 (Volume 212)
  Cabinet card photographs of Lawrie, Clark, Meyer, Carpenter, Reynolds and Hurley families, including men, women and children, woman with a dog.
- Carte-de-visite and cabinet card album of unidentified persons and European locations, undated; 14051 (Volume 213)
  Includes tintypes; includes actors and other celebrities; views depicting various ethnic or national costume; two examples of spirit photographs; views of Switzerland, Germany and possibly other locations.
- [Album views in New York City], [1930-1939]; 14049 (Volume 214)
  Views in Central Park, including winter views with snow, the reservoir, and surrounding buildings; Hampshire House on Central Park South; buildings on Fifth Avenue; Park Avenue, including aerial views, postcard of apartment courtyard, group of women in court of 277 Park Ave., truck in the shape of a roll of Lifesavers, other buildings along Park Ave.; buildings around Gramercy Park; 301 East 21st; 10 East 39th St.; photographers include Stadler, Underwood and Underwood.
- Portraits of relatives, notables and professional associates of Tom Thumb ... from the collection of his widow, the Countess Magri, undated; 14047 (Volume 215)
- [Photographs of the American West], [1900]; 14045 (Volume 216)
  Views of men hunting and fishing in the west, including a clergyman; showing off trophies in front of tents; wagons, and men on horseback; military encampment; soldiers including an African American and Indians; family in front of a cabin; mine buildings; interior view with woman and soldiers; group with tennis rackets; group portraits of women and soldiers on steps of a building; excursion into a canyon.
- Collection of Historical paintings of the Revolutionary War by John Ward Dunsmore in the gallery of the Sons of the Revolution, Fraunces Tavern, [1920 and later]; 14043 (Volume 217.1)
- Collection of Historical paintings of the Revolutionary War by John Ward Dunsmore in the gallery of the Sons of the Revolution, Fraunces Tavern, [1920 and later]; 14042 (Volume 217.2)
  Dunsmore, John Ward, 1856-1945; self-portrait; Dunsmore in his studio, with painting, and props; copies of his paintings depicting scenes from the Revolutionary War, some of which were reproduced in the Pageant of America.
- Volume 218, 14040
  Separated Materials note
  Album 218, Building the George Washington Bridge / photographs by Ernest L. Scott, has been separated from the Album File and is now part of PR 137, George Washington Bridge Construction Photograph Collection.
- [Newspaper cuttings collected by Kate Olcott], [1894]; 14039 (Volume 219)
  Primarily portraits of contemporary and historic persons, most annotated with life dates, and with index by name in the front.
- A cup of friendship just for you for Florrie and Marjorie, [1948]; 14037 (Volume 220)
  "Photographs by Voorhees -- Inc. Portraits of distinction" on inside from cover; snapshots by Frank[?] or Mabel[?] Vorhees of friends including the Jim Blauvelts, "Countess Voorhensky," Dr. Neida Ogden, the Martines and others at Nyack, and in New York at dinner at Dora's and at the "Russian Party."
- [Photographs and postcards of the U.S., including New York, New Jersey, and other locations], [1910-1930]; 14035 (Volume 221.1)
  Mounted in used logs books with heading "Physician's Daily Report" visible on many of the pages; bulk of photographs are from the 1920s, with some earlier and later; has postcard of the totem pole in Pioneer Square, Seattle, on the cover.
- [Photographs and postcards of the U.S., including New York, New Jersey, and other locations], [1910-1930]; 14034 (Volume 221.2)
  Bulk of photographs are from the 1920s, with some earlier and later; has an image labeled Manhasset, Long Island on the cover; images not in any particular order, with rural images on the same page as images of the Plaza Hotel.
- [Whitehouse family albums Vol. 1], [1872-1889]; 14032 (Volume 222.1)
  Cabinet card photographs; the Whitehouse family, including Harry R. Whitehouse with climbing gear, and J. Norman Whitehouse with tennis racket; various barons and marquis's, and others.
- [Whitehouse family albums Vol. 2], [1872-1889]; 14031 (Volume 222.2)
  Whitehouse, and Serrell families and others, including British and European royalty and other celebrities; cartes-de-visite.
- [Album of photographs of Cuba], [1899]; 14029 (Volume 223)
  Photographs (some by LaMarque) before and after the Spanish American War, including Gen. Leonard Wood at his desk and with other officers, views of Morro Castle; soldiers with artillery; batteries, forts, blockhouses, barracks, stables, commissary, etc.; streets and scenery in and around Santiago; Manzanillo; Guantanamo; Daiquiri, including beach and cottages. See also Album #224
- Views of the province of Santiago de Cuba / Captain James G. Harbord, 11th U.S.Cavalry, [1899]-1901; 14027 (Volume 224)
  Views in Cuba, including the transport Wright at dock, government wharf, ice plant, Nautical club, ladies bath, steam launch "Santiago", Yellow fever hospital, Orphelin's' Asylum, Hospital Civil, old Spanish Tower, Plaza de Dolores, stone cutting engine, Cathedral, waterworks, exhibit of photographs labeled "Buffalo Exhibit," probably the Pan American Exposition at Buffalo, harbor and other piers, railroad station, jail, including man whitewashing columns, officers' hospital, interior view of courtroom, group of men on patio, Afro-Cubans with cart, "a typical cabin," a church, Arsenal, San Carlos Club including interior, offices, dos Bocas, train in the countryside, Cayo Toro, Spanish fort, tents to the right, Santa Ursula battery, Sta. Ines Fort, Cay Ratones; photographs by L. LaMarque. See also album #223.
- [Album of engravings of 19th century and earlier personalities], [1860]; 14025 (Volume 225)
  Portrait engravings, primarily by John Sartain, many for the Eclectic Magazine; includes portraits of European monarchs and aristrocrats, including both contemporary and historic figures; British and American authors including Shakespeare and his contemporaries, Walter Scott and his literary friends, the Brownings, American legal and political figures, Louis Agassiz and other scientists and educators, a self-portrait of Sartain, and an engraving of the donor after a daguerreotype by Root; A Midsummer's Night Dream, after Landseer, and historic scenes, such as the Death of General Wofle at Quebec, 1759.
- [New York City scrapbooks], undated; 14023 (Volume 226.1)
- [New York City scrapbooks], undated; 14022 (Volume 226.2)
- [New York City scrapbooks], undated; 14021 (Volume 226.3)
  Eames, Wilberforce 1855-1937, compiler. Views of New York city homes, business, churches, etc., most lithographs made for Valentine's Manual; maps, some from Valentines; text from various sources.
- Atlas of plates, illustrating the geology of the state of Maine, accompanying the first report on the geology of that state, by Charles T. Jackson, M.D. state geologist.: Published by order of the legislature of Maine. -- [Boston :Thomas], [1837]; 14019 (Volume 227)
  Lithographs of scenery and geologic formations in Maine; fossil shells; stone strata, waterfalls of the River St. John, Mt. Katahdin from W. Butterfields, view down St. Croix River, Pulpit Rock, view from Eastport, West Quoddy-Head, Buck's Harbour, Mt. Desert, Cape Rosier, Camden and Kennebec Bay, Migonticook Mountains; Francis Graeter, del., Thomas Moore, Lith.; most plates hand-colored.
- [Webb Family carte-de-visite album], [1860-1879]; 14017 (Volume 228)
  Album of mostly cartes-de-visite with some cabinet cards, including one of a cat; most are unidentified, except a few of Francis Egerton Webb; includes many photographs of children, and one of a dog; includes European photographers.
- [Webb Family album], [1860-1889]; 14015 (Volume 229)
  Cartes-de-visite, cabinet cards and tintypes, mostly unidentified except for James Watson Webb, 1802-1884, G. Creighton Webb, F. Egerton Webb, and Mrs. James Webb; included European photographers; soldiers, women in costumes and ball dress, views of European scenes.
- Faculty and students, Packard's Business College, 1874; 14013 (Volume 230.1)
  Portraits and group portraits of faculty and students, some identified; Julius Brill, photographer.
- Faculty and students, Packard's Business College, 1875; 14012 (Volume 230.2)
  Portraits and group portraits of faculty and students, some identified.
- Faculty and students, Packard's Business College, 1876; 14011 (Volume 230.3)
  Portraits and group portraits of faculty and students, some identified; P.C. Duchochois, photographer.
- Faculty and students, Packard's Business College, 1879; 14010 (Volume 230.4)
- Faculty and students, Packard's Business College, 1880; 14009 (Volume 230.5)
- [Album of commercial photographs of Europe, Canada and the United States], [1880-1889]; 14007 (Volume 231)
  Photographs, probably collected during travels, including views by George Washington Wilson, and William Notman; views of England, including interiors of palaces and churches and a parade; Brussels; Anvers; copy of a paintings; the Hague; Amsterdam; young men with hunting dogs; Drummond Castle and Gardens; views along the Canadian Railroad by Notman, including views in Montreal, and in the Rockies; Niagara Falls; Fifth Avenue, Brooklyn Bridge and the Bowery in New York City.
- Construction of the Broadway and 7th Ave. cable line, 1891; 14005 (Volume 232)
  Views of the construction, including workers and track on Broadway, mazes of pipes underground, stacks of cobblestones, posters advertising Bill Nye's "The Cad' at the Union Square Theatre, men in bowlers, including J.D. Crimmin; details of equipment; views around Union Square and Bowling Green.
- [Scrapbooks of views of New York city and state], [1910-1939]; 14003 (Volume 233.1)
- [Scrapbooks of views of New York city and state], [1910-1939]; 14002 (Volume 233.2)
- [Scrapbooks of views of New York city and state], [1910-1939]; 14001 (Volume 233.3)
  Wallin, Mathilda K., M.D. Scrapbooks of scenes in New York city, and on the Hudson, most are halftone reproductions of earlier works including engravings, etc.: streets, parades, houses, churches, farms, harbor scenes; many of the views are from about 1910-1920s, with later clippings, including color items.
- Photographs of Residence, No. 2 West 52nd Street, 1898; home of Mr. & Mrs. Elliot F. Shepard, 13999 (Volume 234)
  Exterior and interior views including view of Mrs. Elliott F. Shepard sitting at desk.
- [Album of photographs of Cuba made or collected by Col. Oswald Ernest while Inspector General of Cuba, 1899], 13997 (Volume 235)
- Card album [of wood engravings from English magazines], [1880-1889]; 13995 (Volume 236)
  Social life and customs in England, including dining, dancing, shopping, playing tennis, rowing, and courtship.
- Pamphlets and booklets from the New York Worlds Fair of 1939-1940 / Donald Dietz, 13993 (Volume 237.1)
  Includes recipe booklets, commercial advertising; snapshots; and booklets from various countries; pins and other souvenirs.
  4 vols. In 2; volumes were photocopied, and items removed and rehoused.
- Pamphlets and booklets from the New York Worlds Fair of 1939-1940 / Donald Dietz, 13992 (Volume 237.2)
  Railroads, Consolidated Edison, a map of the fair and the area, snapshots, postcards, booklets from various state buildings.
- Pamphlets and booklets from the New York Worlds Fair of 1939-1940 / Donald Dietz, 13991 (Volume 237.3)
  Railroad and other transportation booklets, snapshots, product exhibit booklets, postcards.
- Pamphlets and booklets from the New York Worlds Fair of 1939-1940 / Donald Dietz, 13990 (Volume 237.4)
  Paraphernalia such as match books, postcards snapshots and newspaper articles.
- [Engravings, proof book of Lacewood Sanford], [1830-1839]; 13988 (Volume 238)
  Lacewood Sanford, 1817-1890, active 1830s- ?
- Presented by John B McDonald to James Bradley as a remembrance of the part taken by him in the construction of the Rapid Transit Railroad in the City of New York, October 25, 1904, 13986 (Volume 239)
  Views of construction, etc. and men associated with building the subway.
- Residence of Nicholas Fish, Tuxedo Park, NY, 1899; 13984 (Volume 240)
  Exterior view with man and buggy; interior views of parlors, office, dining room, bedrooms.
- Kodaks, Vol. 1, April 29-September 5, 1891, California, Washington, British Columbia, 1891, Apr. 29 - 1891, Sep. 5; 13982 (Volume 241)
  Travel views made with early Kodak camera in California, Washington, British Columbia.
- Kodaks, Vol. 2, September 13, 1891-December 26, 1891, British Columbia, Idaho, Utah, California, Mexico, 1891, Sep. 13 - 1891, Dec. 26; 13980 (Volume 242)
  Travel views made with early Kodak camera in British Columbia, Idaho, Utah, California, Mexico.
- [Album 1 of photographs depicting the construction of Fort Tryon Park by Olmstead Bros., landscape architects, and Edward J. Carrillo, chief engineer], 1930-1934; 13978 (Volume 243)
  Titled variously Claremont Park, and Fort Tryon Park. General views of the construction of Claremont Park, between Riverside Church and the International House, with Grants Tomb to the west, details of stairways, retaining walls, water pipes and drains; postcards and photographs of various locations in Europe which served as sources.
  6 vols. each album labeled with Project title, Olmstead Bros., name of engineer, Edward J. Carrillo, and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Photographers include E.S. Keogh, Irving Underhill, A.H.H., F.F.B., J.B.M., D.M. Jones, L. Funk, J.C.T., E.S.K., J.H.K., Russell & Co., G.R. Fist.
- [Album 1A of photographs depicting the construction of Fort Tryon Park by Olmstead Bros., landscape architects, and Edward J. Carrillo, chief engineer], 1930-1934; 13977 (Volume 243.2)
  Corbin Place Bridge, and Main Underpass Bridge: excavation of approaches, construction of bridges, excavation of underpass, construction of bridge, including setting stones in place, and images with Jack Carrillo identified, other images laid in, including view with George Washington Bridge, looking north to the Palisades, Broadway and Dyckman, Broadway and Thayer, children in wading pool.
- [Album 2 of photographs depicting the construction of Fort Tryon Park by Olmstead Bros., landscape architects, and Edward J. Carrillo, chief engineer], 1930-1934; 13976 (Volume 243. 3)
  Main Terrace, North Terrace, Bridge Connecting Terraces, Playground, Construction, Broadway Wall, Riverside Drive Wall, General views, Fieldhouse: paths, bridges, terraces, views from gardens, panorama of east slope from vicinity of Fort George, planting dogwoods on shelf, steam shovel moving rocks, cement mixer delivering cement used in wading pool, subway entrance and police booth.
- [Album 3 of photographs depicting the construction of Fort Tryon Park by Olmstead Bros., landscape architects, and Edward J. Carrillo, chief engineer], 1930-1934; 13975 (Volume 243.4)
  Main Walk #1 to Walk #25, inclusive, Concession Bldg., Overlook Shelter, Walk 16, East Slope Comfort Station; stone laying, seat construction, planting elms, model of concession building, details of viaducts, including railings, and lighting.
- [Album 4 of photographs depicting the construction of Fort Tryon Park by Olmstead Bros., landscape architects, and Edward J. Carrillo, chief engineer], 1930-1934; 13974 (Volume 243.5)
  Walk 28 to Walk 60, inclusive, Bennett Ave. Addition, North and East Slope Panoramas, fan chamber, Alpine garden including the grotto, North Slope Comfort station, Museum approach walls, image with Jack Carrillo's dog in it, views that include the Sobol Bros. Gas station.
- [Album 5 of photographs depicting the construction of Fort Tryon Park by Olmstead Bros., landscape architects, and Edward J. Carrillo, chief engineer], 1930-1934; 13973 (Volume 243.6)
  Tree moving, Samples, Belgian block, street lamps, sign posts, seats, Bridges and details in Central Park, rock filled slopes, stone walls and other architectural details for reference (not in Fort Tryon--some in Maryland, California, Massachusetts, Washington D.C., on Rockefeller's estate in Pocantico Hills, and other locations). flagpole model, tractor at work.
- [Photographs by Victor Dahle], [1950-1959]; 13971 (Volume 244.1)
- [Photographs by Victor Dahle], [1950-1959]; 13970 (Volume 244.2)
  Scenes in Manhattan and Brooklyn, a ship in NY harbor, scenes in an Orthodox church, parades, fire scenes, portraits of a baby, portraits of women, including cheesecake shots.
- [Album of photographs of military personnel, and scenes during the Spanish American War], 1898; 13968 (Volume 245)
  Views including camp scenes, drills, going on leave, "matching" on payday; officer on pillared porch; views on the Battery, Charleston, S.C.; on board transport going to Puerto Rico; landing at Ponce harbor, July 28; scenes in camp beyond Ponce and other camps; scenes around Puerto Rico, including people, towns, war destruction; reconnoitering on horseback, artillery shelling blockhouse; reporter from Pittsburgh in camp; waterfalls and other scenery, African American man, "Jake"; Puerto Rican employed in camp, and their children; clothes being issued; Puerto Ricans getting licenses to "sell within our lines"; pack trains, and wagon parks; interpreter; on deck of the Minnewaska, bound for New York; other units pictured including 16th Pennsylvania Cavalry, 3rd Artillery, and 3rd Wisconsin. See also album #235.
- [Album of color snapshots of Operation Sail, July 4, 1976], 13966 (Volume 246)
  Images made when Eleanor Katz was the guest of Irving Strauss when he was invited to view Operation Sail from the aircraft carrier U.S.S. Forrestal; the invitation and the U.S.S. Forrestal; views of the tall ships on the East River and ships and the Statue of Liberty on July 3; 59th Street pier in Brooklyn and views enroute to the Forrestal; fireboat spraying fountains of water; tall ships and small craft in New York Harbor; views on deck of the Forrestal, including the arrival of President Ford by helicopter, officers and guests, sailor hotdog vendors; Pres. and Mrs. Ford, and Mittendorf; group portraits of Katz and Strauss and others; sunset views of the harbor.
- [Album of portraits of European and American celebrities], [1890-1899]; 13964 (Volume 247)
  Clippings from popular press and other sources of contemporary and historic persons, including Czar Nicholas, Abraham Lincoln and others.
- California Scenery / published by Taber, Photographer. San Francisco, Cal., [1880-1889]; 13962 (Volume 248)
  5X8 in. views of San Francisco: general views of the town, Golden Gate, hotels, ferry building, Woodward's Gardens, mansions, cable cars, Observatory in Golden Gate Park, Cliff House, Seal rocks, Chinese Josh House, interior of Chinese restaurant, alley in Chinatown; street view in Oakland; Monterey: general view, Hotel del Monte, including club house and garden, beach, bath house, Cypress Point, adobe buildings at Fremont's fort; Carmel Mission; Yosemite views including mountains, lakes and waterfalls; redwood trees.
- [Album of views of Hawaii and other locations], [1880-1889]; 13960 (Volume 249)
  Views in Bermuda, including Hamilton Hotel, Paget, scenery near Governor's, harbor scenes and churches, parks, homes, blacks in donkey carts; Hawaii: portrait, possibly of Liliuokalani; bridges, grass house, Queen's Hospital, Royal Palace, large mansions, general views, streets in Honolulu, waterfront, women in hula costume holding guitars and ukeleles, leper settlement, hula dances out of doors, cane plantation, government House, the prison, field of Easter lilies; view of church and large house on separate mount laid in (accession date from this photo), signed on verso C.A. Beekman and dated 1890; two copies of sentimental pictures: a girl in mantilla and holding a fan and a soldier and a woman embracing; 3 views, possibly from Africa, men with spears, group smoking from hookah, group near tents.
- State Officers and members of the legislature, State of New York, 1868; 13958 (Volume 250)
- Photographs of the Members of the Assembly of the State of New York, 1880, published by McDonnald & Sterry, 520 Broadway, Albany, N.Y., 13956 (Volume 251)
- Legislature, 1866; New York State, 13954 (Volume 252)
- New York State Assembly, 1867; 13952 (Volume 253)
- Assembly photographs, 1861 [New York State], 13950 (Volume 254)
- Photographic Senatorial Album of the State of New York, 1878-79, published by R. E. Churchill, Photographers, Albany, N.Y., 1878-1879; 13948 (Volume 255)
- Photographic album of the Constitutional Convention of the State of New York. 1867. Published by Churchill & Denison, photographers, Albany, N.Y., 13946 (Volume 256)
- Very old New York., [1918]; 13944 (Volume 257)
  Views of New York published in newspapers and as postcards between about 1910 and 1918; includes index arranged alphabetically by subject.
- New York City, parks, 1879-1910; 13942 (Volume 258)
  Compiled by Henry E. Rile; clippings of images depicting New York city parks, including Central Park, Riverside Park, the Speedway at the Jumel Mansion, Bronx Park, Van Cortland Park, Washington Square, Madison Square, Mount Morris Park, Morningside Park, Seward Park, Prospect Park, City Hall Park, Lion park, Pelham Bay Park, the Columbia Yacht Club House; includes winter scenes, including sledding and curling, a coaching parade, also a few trees and scenes not in parks, but showing natural surroundings, including gardens on the Astor Estate, and view on snowy Fifth Avenue.
- New York churches, [not after 1907]; 13940 (Volume 259)
  Compiled by Henry E. Rile; many of the illustrations are clippings from sources earlier and later, 1850s through 1912; index of churches by denomination; includes notes on status of buildings at various times, such as "Spires down, 1895," or "Now a Methodist Church, 1908"; includes interior views.
- Pictures of New York, [1906]-1916; 13938 (Volume 260)
  Compiled by Henry E. Rile; note on inside of notebook reads "1906, commenced the collection"; includes index to images; clippings of houses, public buildings, churches, theaters, historic sites, and events such as the explosion and fire of 1845; notes give date of image, often when structure was built and when it was torn down, altered or destroyed.
- Sites and scenes, Washington Heights vicinity / collected by Reginold Pelham Bolton, [1910-1930]; 13936 (Volume 261)